Intelligent Surveillance System Using Motion
Anomaly Detector. The aim of the project is
firstly to develop a surveillance system that is
beyond conventional or traditional
surveillance system, using motion anomaly
detector to enable to intelligently analyse the
incident reports and be able to alert the
supervisor that there is an issue or there is an
anomaly going on in their vicinity. This
project takes two form of development and two
methodology approach for developing it. The first
iteration makes use of hardware technologies to
develop the main core part of the project. And the
second approach was done based on the software
approach using camera feed as input. And here is
the demonstration of how the project works. This is
the software bundled as EXE executable file on
Windows. So it can be run by just double clicking on
it. So immediately I double click on this, it will open up
in its own self-contained browser, done with Flask
Web GUI. So this will load the web dashboard and
show the incident that has been reported for today. So
I can browse the video footage here. So the system
has been connected to this router, and this router
has been connected to this phone.
my mobile phone. So here it is now.. I'm going to my
browser and it's running on port 5000. So I can
enter it and refresh. So you can see it loads up the
web dashbord directly from the mobile phone. So
from the mobile phone, wherever I am connected to
this router, I can actually start the
surveillance system right from the mobile phone.
But before I start the surveillance system,
there's a settings that needs to be done, which is
like, as part of making it a do it yourself project
in such a way that user can configure this and have
access to their data. So a telegram bot's token and
the chat ID needs to be obtained. And the
instruction for obtaining it has been detailed
here.
So since I already have this, I'll just go back to
this web dashboard and put in the ID. So this is bot
token and the group ID. and I will save this. Then I
can now start the system right here from my phone.
When I click on start, it will trigger the camera
and it will start recording. So the system is
already running and it has been placed in such a way
that it is facing the wall. So it's not recognizing
an object. So I'll just simulate an anomaly by
trying to run. So when I run, it will detect this.
Immediately it detect that it will send a notification
to the telegram group. You can see it is sending a
notification. You can see that the camera  surveillance
stem has detected an anormaly. So I can come here to
the telegram group that I configured and see what
actually happened. So you can see the surveillance system
has detected one object and started recording.
And the same thing here on phone. So I can go back to
the web dashboard and I can review all these
incidents. You can see it's recorded. This was when I
actually ran And I can decide to delete this. I can
toggle the metadata. I can toggle the metadata to
see what actually happened. So it will show
using bonding box to actually show the movement
direction of the objects. At this time, this
object will stationary move to the right. It was
stationary later. So you can see. The
implementation of this project is in four phases.
In the first phase, which is the frame, Python
OpenCV was largely leveraged for getting
the frame from the camera. And when the frame is
gotten, the detection was performed using
Supervision and Ultralytics and YOLO
state-of-the-art model that was discovered in
the course of this research. The third phase
involves tracking, which is the phase whereby the
metadata of the video or the incident
recognised is being saved and the bounding box of this
object are used to determine the movement direction of
the particular object. And the last phase involve
sending out this as a saved file. In terms of the
recorded video, the metadata so that it can be sent
to the web dashboard. The web dashboard was developed using
Flask. And this self-contained browser was done using
Flags WEB GUI so that the application can serve and
stand alone application. Thank you so much for checking this out.